Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
- XIII. Processing of intelligence (Boxes 106-183, 229-240, 243)
  - d. Headquarters circulars (Boxes 157-169)
    - (2) Warning lists (Boxes 159-169)
      - 1894 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 6-8)
        Includes 92 circulars numbered 162-9344 and a roster of expelled foreign nationals. Circular no. 1800 gives a biographical and political police account of 195 people and a roster of names taken off the watch list.
      - 1895 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 9-10)
        Available on microfilm reel 292
        82 circulars numbered from 430-10882.
      - 1896 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 11-12)
        Available on microfilm reels 292-293
        82 circulars numbered from 53-11121.
      - 1897 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 13-14)
        Available on microfilm reel 293
        84 circulars numbered from 524-11384.
      - 1898 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 15-17)
        Available on microfilm reel 294
        Includes roster of foreigners expelled from Russia from 1894-1898.
      - 1899 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 18-19)
        Available on microfilm reels 294-295
        46 circulars numbered from 132-2263.
      - 1900 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 20-21)
        Available on microfilm reel 295
        46 circulars from 43-2862.
      - 1901 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 22-23)
        Available on microfilm reel 296
        41 circulars from 131-4292.
      - 1902 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 24-27)
        Available on microfilm reels 296-298
        66 circulars from 111-8268 and roster of foreigners expelled from Russia.
      - 1903 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 28-30)
        Available on microfilm reels 298-299
      - 1904 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 31-33)
        Available on microfilm reels 299-301
        38 circulars from 630-14771. Circular no. 5500 includes the police background on Dzhugashvili (Stalin).
      - 1905 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 34-36)
        Available on microfilm reels 301-302
        47 circulars from 132-14994.
      - 1906 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 37-40)
        Available on microfilm reels 302-303
        Includes roster of persons permitted to go abroad instead of being exiled to Siberia.
      - 1907 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 41-43)
        Available on microfilm reels 303-304
        30 rosters. The numbering system for Headquarters biographic cards begins with this volume of circulars, with numbers up to 5152.
      - 1908 (Index XIIId(2), Folder 44)
        Available on microfilm reel 304
        14 rosters numbered to 10673.
      - 1909 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 45-47)
        Available on microfilm reel 305
        Includes printed rosters numbered to 16949.
      - 1910 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 48-49)
        Available on microfilm reel 306
        41 rosters with file numbers for biographical cards up to 20332.
      - 1911 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 50-52)
        Available on microfilm reels 307-308
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards from 20336-22800.
      - 1912 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 53-54)
        Available on microfilm reels 308-309
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards up to 25537.
      - 1913 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 55-56)
        Available on microfilm reels 309-310
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards up to 28595.
      - 1914 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 57-58)
        Available on microfilm reels 310-311
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards up to 32013.
      - 1915 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 59-60)
        Available on microfilm reels 311-312
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards from 32014-34833.
      - 1916-1917 (Index XIIId(2), Folders 61-62)
        Available on microfilm reel 312
        Rosters with file numbers for biographical cards to 39341.
    - (3) Warnings on dismissed agents (Box 169)
      This collection gives some insight into Okhrana practices within Russia with regard to security checking and other counter-intelligence activities for purposes of weeding out or keeping out of the service unreliable agents. These circulars, dated from 1909 to 1916, refer to particular individuals whose services had been proven as unreliable or whose loyalties were subject to questioning. In some cases, no reasons for dismissal are given; in others it is obvious that decisions were made on the basis of investigation.
      Only one of these documents is actually a roster of a large number of such dismissed agents. In it a statement is made that the individuals were supplying the service with information but were proven as unreliable or actually provocateurs on behalf of the revolutionaries.
      Available on microfilm reel 313
      - 1909 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 1)
      - 1910 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 2)
      - 1911 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 3)
      - 1912 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 4)
      - 1913 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 5)
      - 1914 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 6)
      - 1915-1916 (Index XIIId(3), Folder 7)
  - e. Journals for incoming and outgoing messages (Boxes 170-173, 173A)
    A journal or log book of incoming and outgoing dispatches was probably kept from the very beginning of the Okhrana service in Paris. The files, however, contain only the journals dating back to the year 1891, one book for the first ten years for each, incoming and outgoing. These entries were nothing more than a record-keeping device and a check upon what messages had been attended to. Some entries give brief statements of the contents or comments concerning replies to communications.
    Available on microfilm reels 313-316
    - Incoming messages
      - 1891-1901 (Index XIIIe, Folder 1)
      - 1901-1904 (Index XIIIe, Folder 2)
      - 1902-1905 (Index XIIIe, Folder 3)
      - 1905-1907 (Index XIIIe, Folder 4)
      - 1908-1909 (Index XIIIe, Folder 5)
        Available on microfilm reel 314
      - 1910-1911 (Index XIIIe, Folder 6)
      - 1912-1915 (Index XIIIe, Folder 7)
      - 1916-1917 (Index XIIIe, Folder 8)
    - Outgoing dispatches
      - 1891-1902 (Index XIIIe, Folder 9)
      - 1901-1904 (Index XIIIe, Folder 10)
      - 1902-1904 (Index XIIIe, Folder 11)
        Available on microfilm reel 315
      - 1908 (Index XIIIe, Folder 12)
      - 1910-1911 (Index XIIIe, Folder 13)
      - 1912 (Index XIIIe, Folder 14)
      - 1913 January-July (Index XIIIe, Folder 15)
      - 1913 August-December (Index XIIIe, Folder 16)
      - 1914 (Index XIIIe, Folder 17)
      - 1914-1915 (Index XIIIe, Folder 18)
      - 1915-1916 (Index XIIIe, Folder 19)
        Available on microfilm reel 316
      - 1916 (Index XIIIe, Folder 20)
      - 1917 (Index XIIIe, Folder 21)
  - f. Index card system (Boxes 173, 229-240, 243)
    - (1) Reference card index files on
      - (a) Individuals
        - Main operational index file
          Contains about 85,000 cards giving the surname and, in most instances, the given name and patronymic of various individuals. References to incoming, outgoing dispatches, circulars, or other documents are also recorded. In some instances, the cards also give the individual's alias, occupation, party, or subversive affiliation, photograph available, and reference to his residence. Among the entries are references also to spies (working for foreign governments) and to deserters from the Russian services
          Contains about 85,000 cards in Russian rearranged in Roman alphabetical order as follows: a, b, c (Russian CH), d, e, f, g, h (Russian KH), i, k, l, m, n, o, p, r, s (includes Russian SH and SHCH), t, u (Russian IA and IU), v, z (includes Russian ZH). Entries for the letters S-T were filmed slightly out of sequence.
          - Aage-Alekseev (Box 230A)
            Available on microfilm reel 403
          - Alekseev-Apraksin (Box 230A)
            Available on microfilm reel 404
          - "Apsis"-Azef (Box 230A)
            Available on microfilm reel 405
          - Azef-Bariatinskii (Boxes 230A, 230B)
            Available on microfilm reel 406
          - Baryshnikova-Berzin (Box 230B)
            Available on microfilm reel 407
          - Berzin-Bliumenfel'd (Box 230B)
            Available on microfilm reel 408
          - Bliumenfel'd-Boiartsev (Boxes 230B, 230C)
            Available on microfilm reel 409
          - Boiartsev-Budkevich (Box 230C)
            Available on microfilm reel 410
          - Budo-Bzheski (Box 230C)
            Available on microfilm reel 411
          - Chachin-Chistoserdov (Box 230C)
            Available on microfilm reel 412
          - Chistoserdov-Diakonov (Boxes 230C, 230D)
            Available on microfilm reel 413
          - Diakova-Dolinda (Box 230)
            Available on microfilm reel 414
          - Dolinda-Eikhman (Box 230)
            Available on microfilm reel 415
          - Eikhner-Eropkina (Boxes 230D, 230E)
            Available on microfilm reel 416
          - Eropkina-Fetskin (Box 230E)
            Available on microfilm reel 417
          - Fevarot-Frol'kis (Box 230E)
            Available on microfilm reel 418
          - Frol'kis-Garanzhe (Boxes 230E, 230F)
            Available on microfilm reel 419
          - Garaveli-German (Box 230)
            Available on microfilm reel 420
          - Germann-"Glebushka" (Box 230)
            Available on microfilm reel 421
          - Glik-Gol'dsmit (Box 230)
            Available on microfilm reel 423
          - Gol'dsmit-Gotlib (Boxes 230F, 230G)
            Available on microfilm reel 422
          - Gotovitskii-Groisman (Box 230G)
            Available on microfilm reel 424
          - Groisman-Gus'kov (Boxes 230G, 230H)
            Available on microfilm reel 425
          - Guskvarna-Hmelevskii (Box 230H)
            Available on microfilm reel 426
          - Hmurzhinskii-"Iosif" (Box 230H)
            Available on microfilm reel 427
          - "Ios'ka"-Kameneva (Box 230H)
            Available on microfilm reel 428
          - Kamenskii-Kasper' (Boxes 230H, 230I)
            Available on microfilm reel 429
          - Kasperovich-Kissina (Box 230I)
            Available on microfilm reel 430
          - Kist'-Kolarov (Box 230I)
            Available on microfilm reel 431
          - Kolbasa-Kostovich (Boxes 230I, 230J)
            Available on microfilm reel 432
          - Kostovich-Krigs' (Box 230J)
            Available on microfilm reel 433
          - Krikman-Kuznetsov (Box 230J)
            Available on microfilm reel 434
          - Kuznetsov-Lebedev (Boxes 230J, 230K)
            Available on microfilm reel 435
          - Lebedev-Levin (Box 230K)
            Available on microfilm reel 436
          - Levin-Litvak (Box 230K)
            Available on microfilm reel 437
          - Litvak-Liubimov (Box 230K)
            Available on microfilm reel 438
          - Liubimov-"Maksim" (Boxes 230K, 230L)
            Available on microfilm reel 439
          - "Maksim"-Manuil'skii (Box 230L)
            Available on microfilm reel 440
          - Marmork-Meier (Box 230L)
            Available on microfilm reel 441
          - Meier-Minevskii (Box 230L)
            Available on microfilm reel 442
          - Minin-Moldavan (Box 230M)
            Available on microfilm reel 443
          - Moritts-Naumov (Box 230M)
            Available on microfilm reel 444
          - Naumov-Nordshtrem (Box 230M)
            Available on microfilm reel 445
          - Nordshtrem-Orlov (Boxes 230M, 230N)
            Available on microfilm reel 446
          - "Pavel"-Pire (Box 230N)
            Available on microfilm reel 447
          - Pirino-Pototskaia (Boxes 230N, 230O)
            Available on microfilm reel 452
          - Potlazhan-Raevskii (Box 230O)
            Available on microfilm reel 448
          - Radlov-Rembitskii (Box 230O)
            Available on microfilm reel 449
          - Reper'-Rotshtadt (Boxes 230O, 230P)
            Available on microfilm reel 450
          - Rottshtadt-Rudzit' (Box 230P)
            Available on microfilm reel 451
          - Rud'skii-"Sasha" (Box 230P)
            Available on microfilm reel 453
          - "Sasha"-"Sergei" (Boxes 230P, 230Q)
            Available on microfilm reel 454
          - "Sergei"-Shchegoleva (Boxes 230Q, 230R)
            Available on microfilm reel 455
          - Shchegoleva-Shishkin (Box 230R)
            Available on microfilm reel 456
          - Shishkin-Shreider (Box 230R)
            Available on microfilm reel 457
          - Shreider-Siblei (Box 230R)
            Available on microfilm reel 458
          - Siblin-Speranskii (Box 230R)
            Available on microfilm reel 459
          - Spert'-Srvandstian (Boxes 230R, 230S)
            Available on microfilm reel 460
          - Srvandstian-Tornan' (Boxes 230R, 230S, 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 463
          - Stoliarchik-Teshko (Boxes 230R, 230S, 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 465
          - Stoliarchik-Sysoev (Boxes 230R, 230S, 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 461
          - Sysoev-Uiarskii (Boxes 230R, 230S, 230T, 230U)
            Available on microfilm reel 462
          - Torn'-Tselen (Boxes 230S)
            Available on microfilm reel 464
          - "IU"-Iazykov (Box 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 466
          - "V"-Vasich (Box 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 467
          - Veber-Vinogradov (Box 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 468
          - Vinogradov-Voronov (Box 230T)
            Available on microfilm reel 469
          - Voronov-Zarkhi (Boxes 230U, 230V)
            Available on microfilm reel 470
          - Zarin-Zolov (Box 230V)
            Available on microfilm reel 471
          - Zolov-Zhiull'era (Box 230V)
            Available on microfilm reel 472
        - Pre-1907 operational index
          An earlier operational index file in French containing about 22,655 cards. This file, first started from French and other Western police records on Russians abroad, gives the names, passport records, residence, affiliations and other data on the target individual and on émigrés of interest to the Okhrana. References to dispatches and agent reports are made only in a few entries.
          - A-B (Box 231A)
            Available on microfilm reel 473
          - C (Box 231A)
            Available on microfilm reel 474
          - D-E (Box 231A)
            Available on microfilm reel 475
          - F-I (Boxes 231A, 231B)
            Available on microfilm reel 476
          - J-K (Box 231B)
            Available on microfilm reel 477
          - L-M (Boxes 231B, 231C)
            Available on microfilm reel 479-481
          - K-N (Boxes 231B, 231C)
            Available on microfilm reel 481
          - N-P (Box 231C)
            Available on microfilm reel 482
          - O-S (Boxes 231C, 231D)
            Available on microfilm reel 483
          - T-Z (Box 231)
            Available on microfilm reel 484
        - Police Department index
          Index contains about 7,650 cards, giving names and references to revolutionaries abroad reported on in the Police Department circulars prior to the latter's introduction of biographic cards published by Headquarters. Only the full names and references are given. In Roman alphabetical order.
          - A-B (Box 232A)
            Available on microfilm reel 485
          - C-I (Box 232A)
            Available on microfilm reel 486
          - K-M (Boxes 232A, 232B)
            Available on microfilm reel 487
          - P-R (Box 232B)
            Available on microfilm reel 488
          - R-S (Box 232B)
            Available on microfilm reel 489
          - S-V (Box 232B)
            Available on microfilm reel 490
          - W-Z (Box 232B)
            Available on microfilm reel 491
      - (b) Organizations
        Approximately 5,500 operational reference cards giving the names of organizations and publications advocating a revolution in Russia or sympathetic to the revolutionaries. All subversive, Marxist, anarchist, and minority groups are included. The cards reference dispatches, circulars, telegrams and other documents. Organized in Roman alphabetical order.
        - A-L (Box 233A)
          Available on microfilm reel 492
        - L-R (Box 233A)
          Available on microfilm reel 493
        - R-Z (Box 233A)
          Available on microfilm reel 498
    - (2) Biographic card file
      These cards were published by Okhrana Headquarters as reprints of the texts contained in the rosters collected under XIIId(2) (available on microfilm reels 290-312). There is one card per subject individual, including a reproduction of the police photograph and profile where available.
      The information on the cards follows a standard form, giving the police file number from the roster, full name of the individual, date and place of birth, religion, antecedents, siblings, marital status, and his police record of offenses and punishments. The card also indicates the action to be taken by the Okhrana: arrest, surveillance, etc.
      These cards on file are numbered up to 37,000, while the latest rosters of warning lists, from which these cards were reprinted, number above 39,000.
      - Main index (Boxes 229A-229CC)
      - Asians
        - A-B (Box 229DD)
          Available on microfilm reel 503
        - C-H (Box 229DD)
          Available on microfilm reel 504
        - I-L (Box 229DD, 229EE)
          Available on microfilm reel 505
        - M-O (Box 229EE)
          Available on microfilm reel 506
        - O-S (Box 229EE)
          Available on microfilm reel 507
        - T-Z (Box 229FF)
          Available on microfilm reel 508
        - Z (Box 229FF)
          Available on microfilm reel 509
    - (3) Operational and intelligence topics
      Available on microfilm reels 492-502
      Two small files of cards used for reference purposes for mounting operations and preparing intelligence dispatches.
      - Financial management; targets; codes; operational addresses, etc. (Box 233B)
        Available on microfilm reel 496
      - Index cards to Socialist Revolutionary Party activities (Box 233B)
      - Meetings and conferences (Box 233B)
        Available on microfilm reels 496-497
      - Sensitive operational documents on targets (Box 233B)
        Available on microfilm reel 497
      - Operational file on Zhitomirskii (Box 233B)
      - Deep cover agents (Box 233B)
        Available on microfilm reels 494-495, 497
      - Agentura (Box 233B)
      - USA - Canada (Box 233B)
      - Unions (Box 233B)
      - Illegal use of passports (Box 233C)
      - Photographic operations (Box 233C)
      - Surveillance and espionage (Box 233C)
      - Cities and countries (Box 233C)
    - (4) Photographs
      This portion of the collection was not microfilmed. Digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
      A folder of dispatches in this collection (XIIIf(4)) is illustrative of the growing use of photographic documentation in mounting operations and reporting counter-intelligence. Under Index Number Xg are stored the albums of photographs of important revolutionaries for the use of agents and case officers. This collection of photographs may have served similar purposes, but more likely it was a repository used together with all other biographical and reference material as an aid in the preparation of intelligence reports. Doubtlessly also, the photographic materials were organized in some alphabetical or other order. The complete mix-up of all photographs in boxes when the files were received by the Hoover Institution was probably due to the frantic identification searches by the Investigation Commission of 1917, which contributed greatly to the disorder of the files.
      The dispatches in this folder relate various transmittals of photographs, requests for them, etc. The first seven boxes of photographs are now organized in alphabetical order (Xlllf(4)(a)). Many individuals in the box of group photographs have also been identified. One box contains some portrait-type pictures of leading revolutionaries.
      Included in the collection are three boxes of negatives on glass plates, some still in good condition (Xlllf(4)(b)). Many of these were apparently obtained from various photographic studios in Paris catering to Russian émigrés but under some control by the Okhrana (see Xb).
      Also placed with this collection as a matter of sampling is a collection of Russian and German police records with photographs and anthropometric data on a number of individuals (Xlllf(4)(c)).
      - (a) Prints
        Downloadable PDF Index of Photographic Prints
        Photographic Print Index
        - Abachidze, A., 1914 (Box 236A)
        - Abrakhamov, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Abrahamoff
        - Abramov, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1907-1909 (Box 236A)
        - Abramovich, Rakhil', circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Abramovskii, Eduard, 1893 (Box 236A)
        - Adamovich, Mikhail Prokhorovich, 1911 (Box 236A)
        - Adamskaia, Varvara, 1906 (Box 236A)
        - Adler, Friedrich, 1910 (Box 236A)
        - "Adol'f,", 1910 (Box 236A)
          Also "Solomon"
        - Afanas'ev, Sergei Ivanovich, 1903 (Box 236A)
        - Agafonov, Valerian Konstantinovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Agapov, 1905 (Box 236A)
          Also Sidorenko
        - Agaronian, Avetis, 1915 (Box 236A)
        - Ahrberg, Wilhelmine, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aizenshtadt, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Akinfieva, Ekaterina Dmitrievna, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Also Ekaterina Nikitina, Liza, Mariia, Mikhailova, and Bessel'
        - Alad'in, Aleksei, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Al'berts, Karl Georgievich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aleinikov, Veniamin Markovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - "Aleksandr,", circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksandriiskii, Vul'f Leibovich, 1902 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksandrov, Aleksei Ivanovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksandrov, Grigorii, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksandrov, Ivan Mikhailovich, 1915 (Box 236A)
          Also Jean Alexandroff
        - Aleksandrov, Petr, 1910 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksandrova, Mariia, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Alekseenko, Fedor Nikitich, 1904 (Box 236A)
          Includes photograph of his corpse
        - Alekseevskii, Ivan Ivanovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksinskii, Grigorii Aleksievich, 1913 (Box 236A)
        - Aleksinskii, Mikhail, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Aliev, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Alperine, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Altschuler, 1917 (Box 236A)
        - Amaglobili, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Also Amaglobeli
        - Amaglobili, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Ambrozhevich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Amfiteatrov, Aleksandr, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Also Alexandre Amphiteatroff
        - Anan'eva, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Anan'in, Evgenii, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Andreev, Aleksandr, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Alias Krasov
        - Andreev, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Code name: Kudriavyi
        - Andreev, Andrei Nikiforovich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Andreev, Grigorii Vasil'evich, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Also Georges Andreeff
        - Andrikanis, Nikolai A., circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Andropov, Sergei, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Anguez, Paul Edward, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
          Also: Angez, Auguez
        - Anteyperovitz family, 1917 (Box 236A)
        - Anteyperovitz, Ludwig Stanislavovitz, 1917 (Box 236A)
          French card
        - Antipin, Aleksandr, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - "Apollon,", 1913 (Box 236A)
        - Arbatov, Vladimir, 1911 (Box 236A)
        - Arbatova, Nina, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)
        - Argunov, Andrei, circa 1883-1917 (Box 236A)